<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<BOOK>
<INFO><TITLE>Statutory Interpretation</TITLE>
<LESSON>LCS03</LESSON>
<SUBJECTAREA>Legal Concepts &amp; Skills</SUBJECTAREA>
<EMAILCONTACT></EMAILCONTACT>
<VERSION>03/17/2017</VERSION>
<STATUS></STATUS>
<CAVERSIONREQUIRED>3.1.4</CAVERSIONREQUIRED>
<DISTRIBUTION>CALI</DISTRIBUTION>
<COMPLETIONTIME>30 minutes</COMPLETIONTIME>
<CREATEDATE>2005-07-18 09:59:49</CREATEDATE>
<MODIFYDATE>2017-03-20 13:06:51</MODIFYDATE>
<COPYRIGHTS>Copyright 2005, 2010, 2015 CALI&lt;BR /&gt;All Rights Reserved</COPYRIGHTS>
<CREDITS>Artwork by Eric Molinsky</CREDITS>
<CALIDESCRIPTION><P>This lesson introduces the student to the doctrine and processes involved in interpreting state and federal statutes. Statutes are a critical part of every substantive area of the law, so this is important background for every student, legal professional, lawyer and judge.</P></CALIDESCRIPTION>
<AUTHORS><AUTHOR><NAME>Ronald Benton Brown</NAME>
<TITLE>Professor of Law</TITLE>
<SCHOOL>Nova Southeastern University &lt;BR /&gt;Shepard Broad Law Center</SCHOOL>
<EMAIL></EMAIL>
<PHONE></PHONE>
<WEBADDRESS></WEBADDRESS>
</AUTHOR>
</AUTHORS>
<NOTES>07/18/2005 09:59:49: Book was created&lt;BR /&gt;08/30/2005 DQ 1st review.  Link check; spell checker; page review.&lt;BR /&gt;CEB looked at different version. &lt;BR /&gt;12/08/2005 DQ FINAL review - Link checker;  mapper; sent to Rachael for amazing proofreading :) -- need to place Eric's images before sending to Sam&lt;BR /&gt;12/29/2005 Rachael - FINAL review - spell check; proofread; rewording&lt;BR /&gt;02/15/2006 DQ attach images; review student's work. Mapper.&lt;BR /&gt;02/16/2006 SJG Added to library&lt;BR /&gt;05/31/2006 DQ fixed typo&lt;BR /&gt;10/09/2009 Jess, DQ fixed typos - per author&lt;BR /&gt;04/30/2010 DQ replaced drawlines&lt;BR /&gt;06/14/2010 Jess added ADA tags&lt;BR /&gt;06/06/2012 Matt edited &quot;law student&quot; and &quot;lawyer&quot; language.&lt;BR /&gt;01/20/2015 authors revised. DQ spellcheck; linkcheck; mapper.&lt;BR /&gt;06/22/2016 DQ fixed next page issue&lt;BR /&gt;Revised Summer 2014&lt;BR /&gt;03/17/2017 RS corrected typo&lt;BR /&gt;</NOTES>
<DESCRIPTION><P>This lesson introduces the student to the doctrine and processes involved in interpreting state and federal statutes. Statutes are a critical part of every substantive area of the law, so this is important background for every student, legal professional, lawyer and judge.</P>
<P></P>
<P>Approximate Completion Time:  30 minutes</P>
<BR /><BR /><BR />
<div style='font-size: .8em'>Statutory Interpretation<BR />by
<P>Ronald Benton Brown<BR />Professor of Law<BR />Nova Southeastern University <BR />Shepard Broad Law Center</P>
<P>Copyright 2005, 2010, 2015 CALI<BR />All Rights Reserved<BR />CALI Author Copyright 1999-2017 Center for Computer-Assisted Legal Instruction.</P>
<P>Artwork by Eric Molinsky</P>
<P>This program is distributed to licensees for use in accord with an annual membership agreement for 2018-2019. Use after the expiration of the license period is prohibited.</P>
<P>Version 03/17/2017</P>
</div>
</DESCRIPTION>
<CBKLOCATION></CBKLOCATION>
</INFO>

<PAGE ID="Contents" TYPE="Topics" STYLE="0" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="True" SORTNAME="Contents"><TOC><UL><LI><A HREF="Introduction 1 of 7">Introduction</A></LI><LI><A HREF="Why 1 of 12">Why It's Challenging</A></LI><LI><A HREF="Legislative Intent 1 of 5">Legislative Intent</A></LI><LI><A HREF="Plain Meaning 1 of 7">Plain Meaning v. Purpose Approach</A></LI><LI><A HREF="Linguistic 1 of 7">Linguistic Canons</A></LI><LI><A HREF="Process 1 of 4">Implications of the Legislative Process</A></LI><LI><A HREF="Substantive 1 of 3">Substantive Canons</A></LI><LI><A HREF="Statutes 1 of 6">Statutes Affecting Statutory Interpretation</A></LI><LI><A HREF="Review 1">A Little Review</A></LI><LI><A HREF="Conclusion">Conclusion</A></LI></UL></TOC> <MAPPER ID="67" BOUNDS="708,28,109">  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="Introduction" DEST="1" BOUNDS="140,76,64"/>  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="Why It's Challenging" DEST="3" BOUNDS="214,76,104"/>  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="Legislative Intent" DEST="20" BOUNDS="328,76,88"/>  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="Plain Meaning v. Purpose Approach" DEST="9" BOUNDS="426,76,178"/>  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="Linguistic Canons" DEST="10" BOUNDS="614,76,91"/>  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="Implications of the Legislative Process" DEST="11" BOUNDS="715,76,187"/>  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="Substantive Canons" DEST="12" BOUNDS="912,76,103"/>  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="Statutes Affecting Statutory Interpretation" DEST="17" BOUNDS="1025,76,202"/>  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="A Little Review" DEST="59" BOUNDS="1237,76,79"/>  <BRANCH KIND="12" NAME="Conclusion" DEST="2" BOUNDS="1326,76,60"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Introduction 1 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Introduction 2 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Introduction    1 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Statutes are an important part of our law. </P><P>Law students, graduate students and legal professionals generally start out by studying the decisions in litigated cases, but they should soon discover just how important statutes are. Cases frequently turn on the question of what a statute means. So the earlier in your law or graduate school career that you do this lesson, the better.</P><P>In some areas, such as torts, the statutes add to or modify the common law. Some areas, such as corporations law, are dominated by statutes, while areas like tax and environmental law are entirely based on statutes. So every lawyer or legal professional must be equipped to deal with statutes.</P><P>But exactly what a particular statute means is often uncertain. Figuring out that meaning is a frequent task for lawyers and judges. This process may be called &quot;Statutory Interpretation&quot; or &quot; Statutory Construction.&quot; How that is done is the subject matter of this lesson.</P></TEXT> <NOTES><P>image - Copyright CALI 2005. Drawing by Eric Molinsky. </P><P>06/14/2010 Jess added ADA tag</P><P>06/06/2012 edited &quot;law student&quot; and &quot;lawyer&quot; language to reflect wider demographic. Matt</P></NOTES> <PICTURE SRC="LawyerThinking.jpg">drawing of a woman sitting at a desk thinking </PICTURE> <MAPPER ID="1" BOUNDS="544,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="54" BOUNDS="584,159,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Conclusion" TYPE="Book Page" STYLE="Choose Buttons" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Conclusion"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Learning about statutory interpretation can seem frustrating, but it is something lawyers need to know. Without it, you won't really understand judicial decisions which involve the interpretation of statutes. Without it, you won't know how to advise your clients who might be affected by a statute. Without it, you won't be able to marshal arguments to convince a court to decide in your client's favor. Without it, a judge can't logically decide cases involving the correct application of a statute. </P><P>This lesson has begun your study of statutory interpretation. What you have learned is applicable to both state and federal statutes. However, when you are dealing with a specific problems you will need to do <A HREF="popup://additional research">additional research</A> about the approaches, doctrines, maxims or tools favored or disfavored in that jurisdiction and, possibly, even those which are favored or disfavored by a particular judge.</P><P>. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="2" BOUNDS="2506,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="2524,159,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="2564,159,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 1 of 12" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Why 2 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why    1 of   12"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Why would statutory interpretation be complicated? It sounds like it should be simple. Don't you just read the statute and then know what it means? After all, the meaning of the statute is communicated in words that we use all the time to send or receive messages. Isn't understanding the meaning of a statute the same process as understanding a message? </P><P>Essentially, yes, but we've all had the experience when a message we sent was misunderstood, or when we've misunderstood a message we've received. We've even seen situations in which a message was sent to a number of people and they disagreed as to what it meant.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="3" BOUNDS="762,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="4" BOUNDS="802,159,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 2 of 12" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Why 3 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why    2 of   12"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Language is not an exact tool. That is particularly so for the English language. If you were to flip through the pages of an English dictionary, you would find that almost every word has multiple meanings. Just consider the phrase &quot;statutory construction&quot; which was addressed in the Introduction. For many words, there may even be different shades of meanings. That frequently causes uncertainty as to what the words in a statute mean. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="4" BOUNDS="762,194,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="55" BOUNDS="802,242,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 7 of 12" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Why 8 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why    7 of   12"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Words may have surprisingly different meanings to people of different backgrounds, experiences, or interests. For example, suppose the state legislature passed a statute requiring engineers to be licensed by a state agency. To whom would it apply? </P><P>If you asked people at the university, they would wonder if it applied to the professors in the engineering department. </P><P>At the railroad, they would wonder if it applied to the people who drive the trains. </P><P>The director of maintenance at an office building, whose title is &quot;building engineer,&quot; might wonder if it applies to him.</P><P>Their uncertainty is caused by the inexactness of the term &quot;engineer.&quot; It has multiple meanings and shades of meanings. The person who used the term might have intended it to apply to all of them, some of them, or none of them. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="5" BOUNDS="762,609,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="16" BOUNDS="802,657,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 9 of 12" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Why 10 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why    9 of   12"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>A statute provides that one lane of a highway can be designated an &quot;express lane.&quot; The statute provides that trucks are not allowed to use the express lane and that anyone driving a truck in an express lane can be ticketed and fined $100. </P><P>John has just purchased a huge new sports utility vehicle, i.e., an &quot;SUV.&quot; The SUV has some of the attributes of a car and some of the attributes of a truck. </P><P>John knows about the statute. Will John think he can drive his SUV in the express lane without getting a ticket for violating the statute? </P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Yes.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>No.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Why 10 of 12"><P>John wants to drive his SUV in the express lane, so he will probably focus on the reasons the truck exclusion doesn't apply to SUVs and discount the reasons for thinking it should.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Why 10 of 12"><P>John wants to drive his SUV in the express land, so he will focus on the reasons that the truck exclusion does not apply to SUVs and discount the reasons for thinking it should.</P></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="6" BOUNDS="762,775,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="A" DEST="7" BOUNDS="776,823,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="B" DEST="7" BOUNDS="802,823,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="7" BOUNDS="828,823,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 10 of 12" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Why 11 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why   10 of   12"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Here is the same question but looked at from a different perspective.</P><P>Bob is the driver of a normal-sized car who also knows about the statute allowing for the designation of express lanes where trucks are not allowed. Every day he drives in such an express lane. </P><P>Today, John's huge SUV is in the express lane in front of Bob. Does Bob think John should be ticketed? </P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>No. </P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Yes. </P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Why 11 of 12"><P>I disagree. Bob's drive will be a lot easier if other vehicles, particularly big vehicles like John's huge SUV, are kept out of the express lane. From Bob's perspective, John deserves a ticket.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Why 11 of 12"><P>I agree. Bob's drive will be a lot easier if other vehicles, particularly big vehicles like John's huge SUV, are kept out of the express lane. From Bob's perspective, John deserves a ticket.</P></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>03/17/2017 RS: corrected typo statue to statute</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="7" BOUNDS="762,858,109">  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="A" DEST="8" BOUNDS="776,906,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="B" DEST="8" BOUNDS="802,906,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="8" BOUNDS="828,906,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 11 of 12" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Why 12 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why   11 of   12"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Who is right? John or Bob? To each it seems clear that the statute's meaning is what is most beneficial to him. </P><P>As with so many other legal questions, the answer is, &quot;It depends.&quot;<BR/></P><P>What a statute means is a question of law that must be answered by the courts. Over the years, a number of approaches, doctrines, maxims, and tools have developed for use in statutory interpretation. However, there is no single &quot;right&quot; approach to using them. A jurisdiction might mandate a particular approach, method, tool, or a combination of them. But generally you will discover there is no such simplicity. A particular approach, method, tool, or approach may be favored by one judge, or one jurisdiction, some by another.</P><P>So lawyers and legal professionals must be prepared to: 1) identify which approach, doctrine, maxim, or tool they want to be used, 2) figure out why each may be used and 3) figure out why it may not be used.</P><P>A lawyer representing a client (or a law school in a moot court) must also be able to advocate the use by a court of the approach, doctrine, maxim or tool that will result in a favorable outcome and not the use the approach, doctrine, maxim or tool that will result in an unfavorable outcome. </P></TEXT> <NOTES><P>image - Copyright CALI 2005. Drawing by Eric Molinsky. </P><P>06/14/2010 Jess added ADA tag</P><P>06/06/2012 edited &quot;lawyer&quot; language to reflect wider demographic. Matt</P></NOTES> <PICTURE SRC="ArguingInFrontOfJudge.jpg">drawing of two attorneys arguing in front of a judge</PICTURE> <MAPPER ID="8" BOUNDS="762,941,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="47" BOUNDS="802,989,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Plain Meaning 1 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 2 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Plain Meaning    1 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>The two most popular approaches to statutory interpretation today are the plain meaning approach and the purpose approach. </P><P>In the <B>plain meaning approach</B>, the focus is on the words used and the way they are used. The logic is that the legislature picked these words to express its ideas. In picking these words, the legislature probably had in mind the most commonly accepted meaning of those words. So in interpreting the words of the statute, that's the meaning that the court should use. </P><P>Additionally, grammar and punctuation are to be given their usual effect. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="9" BOUNDS="1198,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="24" BOUNDS="1238,159,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Linguistic 1 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 2 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Linguistic    1 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>A linguistic <A HREF="popup://canon">canon</A> is a rule of interpretation that is based upon the way language is used in the statute. The best known linguistic canons are <B>ejusdem generis</B> and <B>expressio unius est exclusio alterius</B>. These will be explained on the following pages.</P><P>Note that the names of these canons are in Latin. That is evidence of how very long these canons have been around.</P></TEXT> <NOTES><P>10/08/2009 Jess fixed a typo</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="10" BOUNDS="1416,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="39" BOUNDS="1434,159,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="1474,159,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Process 1 of 4" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Process 2 of 4" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Process    1 of    4"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Each legislature has an operational procedure that establishes the way things are normally done. The procedure may be based on official rules or may simply be based upon custom. Whenever there is uncertainty as to what that legislature did in a particular situation, the odds are that it followed its normal procedure. Courts rely upon that probability.</P><P>How does that relate to statutory interpretation? Sometimes it can help resolve an uncertainty as to what a legislature intended at the time of enactment. If one interpretation choice is consistent with normal legislative procedure and the other is not, the court should choose the one that is consistent with normal procedure because it's more probable that that is what the legislature intended. That choice is <B>implied by the normal legislative procedure.</B></P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="11" BOUNDS="1634,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="44" BOUNDS="1674,159,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Substantive 1 of 3" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Substantive 2 of 3" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Substantive    1 of    3"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>As you have seen, a number of <A HREF="popup://canon">canons</A> of interpretation have developed. A <B>substantive canon</B> is based on the subject matter of the the law, such as criminal law, real estate law, family law. Most substantive areas of the law have canons of interpretation. When dealing with a statutory interpretation problem, it is imperative to determine if there is a substantive canon that might be applied in the jurisdiction.</P><P>As an example, let's look at one of the most famous substantive canons. It is in the area of criminal law and it is called the <B>rule of lenity</B>. It provides that any ambiguity in a criminal statute must be resolved in favor of the accused.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="12" BOUNDS="1852,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="32" BOUNDS="1870,159,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="1910,159,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Introduction 3 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Introduction 4 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Introduction    3 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>In each of the following sections, you will be introduced to an aspect of statutory interpretation. These are only introductions. None of these sections completely covers the topic. That would require significant further study.</P><P>Also consider that lawyers and judges are called upon to interpret the language in all kinds of documents, such as the United States Constitution, a state constitution, a will, a contract, a deed, or corporate by-laws. The interpretation of each of these has some similarities to statutory interpretation, but each also has unique features. This lesson <B>only</B> deals with the interpretation of <B>statutes</B>.</P></TEXT> <NOTES><P>image - Copyright CALI 2005. Drawing by Eric Molinsky. </P></NOTES> <PICTURE SRC="LawyerReading.jpg">drawing of a woman sitting at a desk reading</PICTURE> <MAPPER ID="13" BOUNDS="544,277,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="14" BOUNDS="584,325,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Introduction 4 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Introduction 5 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Introduction    4 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Statutes are rules of law that are produced by a legislature, as distinguished from the rules developed in judicial decisions. The states and the federal government have similar processes for creating statutes. The idea for the statute must be presented to the legislature in the form of a <B>bill</B>. The bill must get <A HREF="popup://Legislature">a favorable vote from the legislature</A> and then be sent to the chief executive (the President or the Governor) who can stop it from becoming law by vetoing it. Bills that have been passed by the legislature and manage to avoid getting vetoed are called &quot;<B> acts</B> &quot; because they have been en<B>act</B>ed into law. The enacted law is a statute. Most states and the federal government organize the various statutes into codes such as the United States Code or the Florida Statutes. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="14" BOUNDS="544,360,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="36" BOUNDS="562,408,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="602,408,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Introduction 6 of 7 (4/30/2010 replaced drawlines)" TYPE="Prioritize" STYLE="PMatch" NEXTPAGE="Introduction 6 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Introduction    6 of    7 (   4/  30/2010 replaced drawlines)"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Here are the basic facts of this hypothetical question. </P><P>Bob operates a restaurant in the city of Atlantis which is located in Western County, Florida. In one of the rooms of the restaurant, he operates a bar. He is wondering if he can allow his customers to smoke in that bar even though there is a law prohibiting smoking in the restaurant. </P><P>In the left column are additional facts. Connect each of them with the appropriate statement on the right. </P></QUESTION> <ITEM CATEGORY="2">Western County, Florida enacted a law that prohibits smoking in restaurants</ITEM> <ITEM CATEGORY="1">Florida enacted a law that prohibits smoking in restaurants.</ITEM> <ITEM CATEGORY="3">Bob leased space in a mall for his restaurant.  In the lease is a clause that prohibits smoking in restaurants.</ITEM> <ITEM CATEGORY="2">The City of Atlantis enacted a rule prohibiting smoking in restaurants.</ITEM> <ITEMS>Items</ITEMS> <CATEGORY>This is a state statute.  How to go about interpreting it is the subject of this lesson.</CATEGORY> <CATEGORY>This is a local ordinance.  For interpretation purposes, it is generally treated like a statute despite the differences in the enactment process. So its interpretation is covered by this lesson.</CATEGORY> <CATEGORY>This is not a statute, so how to interpret it is not covered by this lesson.</CATEGORY> <RIGHT NEXTPAGE="Introduction 7 of 7"><P>Good work. You've completed this section.</P></RIGHT> <WRONG NEXTPAGE="Introduction 5 of 7"><P>You have missed something. A clause in a lease is not law, so it could not be a statute or an ordinance. The law passed by the state would be classified as a statute. The law passed by a county or city would classified as an ordinance. </P><P>The approach to interpreting an ordinance is generally the same as the approach to interpreting a statute. That's what will be covered by this lesson. However, interpreting leases is a different matter entirely and not discussed by this lesson.</P></WRONG> <ORDERED>False</ORDERED> <SHUFFLE>True</SHUFFLE> <NOTES><P>04/30/2010 DQ replaced drawlines</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="15" BOUNDS="272,28,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="If right" DEST="46" BOUNDS="260,76,37"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="If wrong" DEST="36" BOUNDS="307,76,46"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="65" BOUNDS="363,76,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 8 of 12" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Why 9 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why    8 of   12"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>How a statute affects a person will probably affect how that person thinks a statute should be interpreted. People are likely to look at the words in the way that is most beneficial to them. </P><P>Consider the hypothetical state statute requiring engineers to be licensed. Suppose a component of that statute was a requirement that licensed engineers had to pay an annual licensing fee. How would that affect the way the statute was viewed by the engineering professors, train engineers and building engineers mentioned earlier? None of them would want to pay the annual fee. From their perspective, the statute shouldn't apply to them. So when they looked at the language, that's the way they would interpret the uncertain language.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="16" BOUNDS="762,692,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="6" BOUNDS="802,740,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Statutes 1 of 6" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 2 of 6" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Statutes    1 of    6"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>The United States Code and the statutes of many states have sections that affect statutory interpretation. These may provide:</P><BLOCKQUOTE>- one or more general rules of interpretation</BLOCKQUOTE><BLOCKQUOTE>- one or more definitions that are applicable to all the jurisdiction's statutes</BLOCKQUOTE><BLOCKQUOTE>- one or more rules of interpretation or definitions that have limited applicability, i.e., they apply only to particular statutes.</BLOCKQUOTE></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="17" BOUNDS="2070,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="33" BOUNDS="2110,159,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Statutes 4 of 6" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 5 of 6" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Statutes    4 of    6"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>In 1995, the <A HREF="popup://NCCUSL">National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws</A> adopted The Uniform Statute and Rule Construction Act. Like other Uniform Acts, this is only a proposal that the NCCUSL presents to the various state legislatures. Until enacted by a state legislature it is only a proposal, although the proposal may be considered of persuasive value by a court. To date, only one state, New Mexico, has enacted the Uniform Statute and Rule Construction Act into law. It has had little effect elsewhere. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="18" BOUNDS="2070,360,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="34" BOUNDS="2088,408,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="2128,408,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="additional research" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="additional research"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Further study and research might be most efficient if begun with the brief overview provided in Brown and Brown, STATUTORY INTERPRETATION: THE SEARCH FOR LEGISLATIVE INTENT (National Institute for Trial Advocacy). Then you can focus in greater depth on a particular method or approach by utilizing the huge treatise, Sutherland, STATUTORY CONSTRUCTION (West/Thompson) or a legal encyclopedia (usually under the topic &quot;Statutes &quot;), particularly one jurisdiction of the statute in need of interpretation. </P></TEXT> <NOTES><P>03/17/2017 RS: corrected typo statue to statute</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="19" BOUNDS="54,56,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Legislative Intent 1 of 5" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Legislative Intent 2 of 5" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Legislative Intent    1 of    5"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>The critical factor in statutory interpretation is <B>legislative intent</B>. In other words, the statute should be interpreted to mean what the legislature intended it to mean. So in interpreting a statute, the first step is to determine what the legislature intended when it voted to approve that statute. That sounds simple enough, but it's not. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="20" BOUNDS="980,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="37" BOUNDS="1020,159,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Legislative Intent 3 of 5" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Legislative Intent 4 of 5" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Legislative Intent    3 of    5"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>How can we say legislative intent is a fiction? Consider the following set of facts.</P><P>A state legislature had forty members. It passed a statute that prohibited people from bringing animals into the park. Did the legislature intend to prohibit blind people entering the park with their guide dogs? </P><P>A survey of the forty legislators reveals that ten legislators voted against the statute for reasons having nothing to do with guide dogs. Of those who voted for it, ten thought it would not prevent guide dogs from being brought into the park; ten thought it would prevent guide dogs from being brought into the park; and ten did not even know what was in the statute when they voted for it. They only voted for it because they were asked to do so by the leaders of their party. What was the legislature's actual intent in regard to guide dogs?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>That guide dogs could be brought into the park because only ten of the legislators thought that would be prohibited by the statute.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>That the statute does not apply to guide dogs because half of the legislators didn't even think about guide dogs.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>That guide dogs could not be brought into the park because a majority of the legislators did not think the statute would prohibit that.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>The legislators did not share one state of mind on the point so the legislature didn't really have an <B>actual</B> intent on this, or any, point.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK><P>D is the correct answer. There really wasn't one state of mind shared by the legislators, so there really isn't one legislative &quot;intent.&quot; Because legislative intent is the critical factor in statutory interpretation, that presents a problem which courts have generally ignored. They simply accept the fiction that there was one legislative intent which can be determined logically. That's what makes statutory interpretation problematic.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Legislative Intent 4 of 5"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Legislative Intent 4 of 5"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="3" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Legislative Intent 4 of 5"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="4" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Legislative Intent 4 of 5"></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="21" BOUNDS="980,277,109">  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="A" DEST="22" BOUNDS="968,325,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="B" DEST="22" BOUNDS="994,325,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="C" DEST="22" BOUNDS="1020,325,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="D" DEST="22" BOUNDS="1046,325,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="22" BOUNDS="1072,325,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Legislative Intent 4 of 5" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Legislative Intent 5 of 5" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Legislative Intent    4 of    5"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>How can legislative intent be determined when it doesn't really exist? </P><P>Courts rely upon objective indicators to reflect what the legislature probably would have had in mind if it had one mind. This may remind you of the <A HREF="popup://Objective Theory of Contracts">Objective Theory of Contracts</A>. Courts use objective factors to deduce what would be the intent of the legislature if the legislature had one intent. But which objective factors should be considered? How should they be used? How much weight should each factor be given? Do the rules vary from state to state? Are the rules different for federal statutes? </P><P>This lesson can't answer all those questions. It is designed to help you understand the basics and realize why there's so much more to learn. The fact that legislative intent is a fiction explains why there can be such disagreements as to the proper way to interpret statutes in general and how to interpret particular statutes.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="22" BOUNDS="980,360,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="48" BOUNDS="998,408,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="1038,408,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Objective Theory of Contracts" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Objective Theory of Contracts"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Under the Objective Theory of Contracts, a person whose conduct would be interpreted to be assent to enter into a contract by a reasonable person in the position of the other party would be bound by that manifestation of intent. Similarly, the legislature by enacting a statute has manifested its intent to turn this bill into a law. In figuring out what that law meant, the legislature would be bound by what appeared to be its intent.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="23" BOUNDS="54,111,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Plain Meaning 2 of 7" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 3 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Plain Meaning    2 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Consider the following hypothetical problem.</P><P>In response to a citizen petition complaining about children being attacked by domestic animals in public parks, the state legislature passed a statute prohibiting animals from being brought into public parks. Bill is a blind person who walked into a park. He brought his guide dog with him. Using the plain meaning approach, did Bill violate the statute?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Yes. His guide dog is an animal which he brought into a public park. The statute prohibits bringing a domestic animal into a public park. So he has violated the statute. That is the plain meaning of the statute.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>No. Everyone knows guide dog aren't subject to normal animal restrictions.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK><P>If the court uses the plain meaning approach to statutory interpretation, Bill violated the statute. The dog is an animal and he did bring it into the park. That's exactly what the language prohibits and that's what the question asks. </P><P>Perhaps this sounds like a bad result to you. However, the question is not whether you (or a court) agrees with the legislature. As long as the legislature does not violate constitutional limits, its decisions control. </P><P>But there's more to statutory interpretation that the plain meaning approach. Therefore, we'll have to learn about other possibilities. </P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 3 of 7"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 3 of 7"></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="24" BOUNDS="1198,194,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="A" DEST="25" BOUNDS="1212,242,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="B" DEST="25" BOUNDS="1238,242,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="25" BOUNDS="1264,242,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Plain Meaning 3 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 4 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Plain Meaning    3 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Another method of statutory interpretation is called <B>the purpose approach</B>. Under the purpose approach, the court should focus on the mischief or evil that the legislature intended to eradicate and interpret the statute to have that effect. </P><P>Sometimes the legislature will state the purpose of the statute in the statute itself or in the <A HREF="popup://preamble">preamble</A> to the act. That is usually done to make it easier for a court to use the purpose approach. If that's not done, the court may have to try to figure out the purpose from other sources.</P><P><B>Legislative history</B> may also be used to determine the purpose of legislation and what the legislature intended. The legislative history includes the reports and documents produced in the enactment process. However, some judges, identified as &quot;textualists,&quot; reject any use of legislative history in the interpretation process.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="25" BOUNDS="1198,277,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="56" BOUNDS="1216,325,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="1256,325,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="preamble" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="preamble"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>A preamble is a statement that appears in the bill before the enacting clause. It generally recites the legislature's reasons for passing the law, e.g., &quot;Whereas this legislature has found the following problem to exist, be it enacted this day that . . . .&quot; By the very terms of the act, what is enacted is what follows the words of enactment. So when the bill is enacted into law, the preamble is not actually part of the new law. Preambles are now becoming less common because legislatures are more likely to recite the legislative purpose in the act itself, i.e., after the enacting clause.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="26" BOUNDS="54,166,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="structure" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="structure"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>The federal government as well as all state governments divides governmental power between three branches: the executive branch, the legislative branch and the judicial branch. Each branch acts as a check and balance on the power of the other two branches. For example, while only the legislature can create new statutes, the executive has the power to veto bills passed by the legislature, thereby preventing them from becoming law. So the executive's power to veto new legislation is a check and balance on the power of the executive. However, only the executive has the power to put the statutes into effect, so that acts as a check and balance on the legislative power. </P><P>Local governments may not follow this model. A city council or county commission may have both executive and legislative power; and the mayor may have no executive veto power. Consequently, ordinances may be enacted simply by getting a majority vote of the city council or county commission. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="27" BOUNDS="54,221,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 4 of 12" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Why 5 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why    4 of   12"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Often the uncertainty of language is latent. That means the uncertainty is not apparent just from reading the language. Latent is distinguished from an ambiguity that is patent, i.e., obvious on its face.</P><P>A latent ambiguity can only be realized when you try to apply those words to a particular set of facts. To illustrate what is meant by latent ambiguity, consider the question on the next page.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="28" BOUNDS="762,360,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="29" BOUNDS="802,408,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 5 of 12" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose Buttons" NEXTPAGE="Why 6 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why    5 of   12"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>A hypothetical state statute provides for an import tax on imported foods. Different tax rates are imposed on different foods. The tax rate on fruits is much higher than the tax on vegetables. Does this language contain a patent ambiguity?</P></QUESTION> <BUTTON>Yes</BUTTON> <BUTTON>No</BUTTON> <BUTTON>Maybe</BUTTON> <FEEDBACK><P>The language on its face is clear. It identifies two categories mutually exclusive categories: fruits and vegetables. Therefore, if the import is a fruit, the fruit rate is charged. On the other hand, if the import is a vegetable, the vegetable rate is charged. There's nothing unclear about that.</P><P>However, there is always the possibility that a latent ambiguity could be hidden beneath the surface of this apparently clear language.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Why 6 of 12"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="2" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Why 6 of 12"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="3" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Why 6 of 12"></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="29" BOUNDS="762,443,109">  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="Yes" DEST="30" BOUNDS="742,491,26"/>  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="No" DEST="30" BOUNDS="778,491,22"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="Maybe" DEST="30" BOUNDS="810,491,40"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="30" BOUNDS="860,491,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 6 of 12" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose Buttons" NEXTPAGE="Why 7 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why    6 of   12"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Let's reconsider the same statute in light of the following facts.</P><P>A shipment of tomatoes has been imported, so the Tax Collector has to collect the tax. Tomatoes are scientifically classified as fruits. However, in the United States, tomatoes are used as vegetables, marketed as vegetables, and treated as vegetables by such things as the nutrition recommendations issued by the United States Department of Health. In fact, the American public generally thinks of tomatoes as vegetables. </P><P>Consequently the tax collector is uncertain whether tomatoes should be taxed at the rate for fruits or vegetables?</P><P>Have we discovered a latent ambiguity?</P></QUESTION> <BUTTON>Yes</BUTTON> <BUTTON>No</BUTTON> <FEEDBACK><P>For some purposes tomatoes are considered fruits, but they are considered vegetables for other purposes. We do not know which way to classify them for the purposes of this statute. That makes the statute ambiguous. Since the ambiguity can only be discovered if we have the additional information that tomatoes, unlike other fruits and vegetables, are not classified consistently, this is a latent ambiguity.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Why 7 of 12"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="2" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Why 7 of 12"></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="30" BOUNDS="762,526,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="Yes" DEST="5" BOUNDS="768,574,26"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="No" DEST="5" BOUNDS="804,574,22"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="5" BOUNDS="836,574,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="canon" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="canon"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>A canon is a rule. It may be embodied in a saying (sometimes referred to as a &quot;maxim&quot;) or referred to by few words or a phrase (possibly in another language such as Latin). </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="31" BOUNDS="54,276,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Substantive 2 of 3" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose Buttons" NEXTPAGE="Substantive 3 of 3" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Substantive    2 of    3"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Consider the following hypothetical facts.</P><P>A federal statute provided that it was a crime to use a firearm while committing a crime. Jack exchanged his pistol for illegal drugs. In other words, the price he paid for the drugs was one pistol. He was convicted of the crime of buying illegal drugs. He was also charged with violating the statute that makes it a crime to use a firearm in the commission of another crime. After carefully reading the language of the statute, the court was uncertain as to whether the legislature intended to put this kind of conduct within the reach of the new statute. Under these circumstances, should Jack be convicted of this additional crime?</P></QUESTION> <BUTTON>Yes</BUTTON> <BUTTON>No</BUTTON> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Substantive 3 of 3"><P>&quot;No&quot; seems to be the better answer. Since the substance of this statute is criminal law, the rule of lenity can be used to resolve the ambiguity. The rule provides that uncertainty in a criminal statute should be resolved in favor of the accused. </P><P>However, if the court decided that the statute was not uncertain or ambiguous, then the rule of lenity would not be applied. </P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="2" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Substantive 3 of 3"><P>&quot;No&quot; is the better answer. The substance of this statute is criminal law, so the rule of lenity could be applied. The rule provides that uncertainty in the meaning of a criminal statute should be resolved in favor of the accused. </P><P>However keep in mind that the rule of lenity is to be used only to resolve an ambiguity. If a court decided the statute was not uncertain or ambiguous, then the rule of lenity would not be applied. </P></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="32" BOUNDS="1852,194,109">  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="Yes" DEST="52" BOUNDS="1858,242,26"/>  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="No" DEST="52" BOUNDS="1894,242,22"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="52" BOUNDS="1926,242,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Statutes 2 of 6" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose Buttons" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 3 of 6" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Statutes    2 of    6"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Let's illustrate this with a hypothetical question. </P><P>A general state statute provides that a word indicating one gender (i.e., male or female) shall be interpreted to include the other gender or no gender unless otherwise specified.</P><P>Another statute in this state requires real estate salesmen to be licensed. Mary wants to go into real estate sales. A friend suggests that Mary will not need a license because it only applies to salesmen and Mary is not a man. Will Mary need a license?</P></QUESTION> <BUTTON>Yes</BUTTON> <BUTTON>No</BUTTON> <FEEDBACK><P>This example is based on actual Florida statutes.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 3 of 6"><P>As pointed out in the text preceding this question, a statute provides that in any other statute words of one gender are considered to include words of the other gender. So the term &quot;salesman&quot; is applicable to women as well as men. </P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="2" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 3 of 6"><P>As pointed out in the text preceding this question, a statute provides that in any other statute words of one gender are considered to include words of the other gender. So the term &quot;salesman&quot; is considered to include &quot;saleswomen. &quot;</P></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>10/09/2009 DQ pre author - deleted &quot;Florida Statute&quot; and added shared response sentence</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="33" BOUNDS="2070,194,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="Yes" DEST="35" BOUNDS="2076,242,26"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="No" DEST="35" BOUNDS="2112,242,22"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="35" BOUNDS="2144,242,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Statutes 5 of 6" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose Buttons" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 6 of 6" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Statutes    5 of    6"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>A question arose as to the proper interpretation of a California statute. The plaintiff's attorney has pointed out to the court that the Uniform Statute and Rule Construction Act requires the judge to first consider the plain meaning of the statute. Is that binding on a California judge?</P></QUESTION> <BUTTON>Yes</BUTTON> <BUTTON>No</BUTTON> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Contents"><P>The Uniform Statute and Rule Construction Act has not been enacted into law in California (or in any other state except New Mexico). So a California judge is not required to follow it, although a California judge may find it persuasive in the absence of binding California authority.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="2" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Contents"><P>The Uniform Statute and Rule Construction Act has not been enacted into law in California (or in any other state except New Mexico). So a California judge is not required to follow it, although a California judge may find it persuasive in the absence of binding California authority.</P></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="34" BOUNDS="2070,443,109">  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="Yes" DEST="67" BOUNDS="2076,491,26"/>  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="No" DEST="67" BOUNDS="2112,491,22"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="53" BOUNDS="2144,491,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Statutes 3 of 6" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 4 of 6" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Statutes    3 of    6"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>In contrast to the prior example, some state or federal statutes may provide a rule of interpretation that is limited in its application. It doesn't apply to all the jurisdiction's statutes. It applies only to a particular part or chapter of the statutes. A good example is found in the Uniform Commercial Code. It provides that the state's version of the UCC is to be interpreted to accomplish its goal of modernizing and simplifying commercial law. </P><P>One jurisdiction may have an approach to one part of its statutes that is totally different from the approach to another part of its statutes. An example is the Florida Legislature has mandated that the state's Marketable Record Title Act is to be <A HREF="popup://liberal construction">liberally construed </A>, while in contrast the state's Construction Lien Law is not to be liberally construed.</P><P>So statutes providing for definitions or methods of interpretation should be carefully examined to determine their scope.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="35" BOUNDS="2070,277,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="18" BOUNDS="2088,325,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="2128,325,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Introduction 5 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Introduction 6 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Introduction    5 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Statutes produced by local governments such as cities and counties are called <B>ordinances</B>. Their enactment process may be different from that of state and federal statutes due to the different <A HREF="popup://structure">structure</A> of local governments, but for interpretation purposes, ordinances are generally treated like statutes.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="36" BOUNDS="544,443,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="65" BOUNDS="562,491,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="602,491,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Legislative Intent 2 of 5" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Legislative Intent 3 of 5" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Legislative Intent    2 of    5"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Intent is a state of mind. So the legislative intent is what the legislature had in mind. But a legislature doesn't have one mind. </P><P>A legislature is made up of lots of <U>individual legislators</U> and each has his or her own mind. If we could look into the minds of the individuals at the moment they voted on this statute, we would discover each had a different thing in mind. Is the legislative intent the sum of all those individual intents? The average of them? The median of them? The sum of those who voted in favor of the bill? No! It's none of those things.</P><P>Therefore, legislative intent is not a real thing. It's a fiction. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="37" BOUNDS="980,194,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="21" BOUNDS="1020,242,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Process 3 of 4" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose Buttons" NEXTPAGE="Process 4 of 4" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Process    3 of    4"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Consider these hypothetical facts.</P><P>In a particular appropriations act, Congress provided one million dollars for the protection of the Western River. At the time when this appropriations act was passed, no federal program existed to protect the Western River. A political action group claims that, by making this appropriation, Congress impliedly authorized the Army Corps of Engineers to create a new program to protect the Western River. However, the Army Corps of Engineers has refused to act because it thinks it lacks the authority to do so. The political action group sued for declaratory judgment. </P><P>Should a judge rule that the Corps was given this authority by the appropriations act? </P></QUESTION> <BUTTON>Yes</BUTTON> <BUTTON>No</BUTTON> <FEEDBACK><P>&quot;No&quot; is the better answer. The claim is that Congress gave the Corps this authority through an appropriations act. However, an appropriations act normally deals only with providing of money for programs, not their creation. It would be unusual for an appropriations act to be used to create a new program. There is nothing to indicate Congress intended to do the unusual thing here. The logical conclusion is that Congress probably intended only to make sure money was available if it later decided to create this program. </P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Process 4 of 4"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="2" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Process 4 of 4"></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="38" BOUNDS="1634,277,109">  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="Yes" DEST="51" BOUNDS="1640,325,26"/>  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="No" DEST="51" BOUNDS="1676,325,22"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="51" BOUNDS="1708,325,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Linguistic 2 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 3 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Linguistic    2 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P><B>Ejusdem generis</B> means of the same class. It is used to narrow a general term that is at the conclusion of a list to the same category as the specific terms in the list. For example, let's take a statute that imposes a tax on the importation of &quot;oranges, grapefruit, limes and others.&quot; Is that tax due on imported grapes? </P><P>The question is whether grapes are included in the general term, &quot;others.&quot; Under ejusdem generis, &quot;others&quot; is limited to the class of specific words that appear in the list. What is the class to which oranges, grapefruit and limes belong? Let's consider some possibilities.</P><BLOCKQUOTE>- They are all plants. So are grapes. Accordingly, the tax should be imposed. </BLOCKQUOTE><BLOCKQUOTE>- Oranges, grapefruit and limes are all fruits. So are grapes. Accordingly the tax should be imposed.</BLOCKQUOTE><BLOCKQUOTE>- Oranges, grapefruit and limes are all citrus fruits. Grapes are not citrus fruits. Using that classification, the taxes should not be imposed. </BLOCKQUOTE><P>You can see identifying the class is a critical factor in applying ejusdem generis.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="39" BOUNDS="1416,194,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="40" BOUNDS="1456,242,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Linguistic 3 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 4 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Linguistic    3 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P><B>Expressio unius est exclussio alterius</B> means that the inclusion of one excludes others. It is also known as the rule of <I>negative implication</I> or the rule of <I>backspin</I>. Under this canon, when a statute provides specifics, particularly a list of specifics, any specific not mentioned is not included by implication. The logic is that it must have been left out on purpose. If the legislature had intended to include things in addition to this list of specifics, it would have added a general term at the end of the list, but it didn't. </P><P>For example, a statute imposes an import tax on: apples, plums, oranges and cherries. Should the tax be charged on grapes? Probably not.</P><P>The logic is that when the legislature listed apples, plums, oranges and cherries, it probably intended to include only those four things. Since grapes were not on the list of specifics, grapes were left out intentionally. The implication of this list of specifics is that it does not include anything else, i.e., it is a negative implication.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="40" BOUNDS="1416,277,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="66" BOUNDS="1456,325,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Linguistic 4 of 7 (4/30/2010 replaced drawlines)" TYPE="Prioritize" STYLE="PMatch" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 4 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Linguistic    4 of    7 (   4/  30/2010 replaced drawlines)"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>In the boxes on the left below are samples of statutory language. On the right are two canons of interpretation, <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">expressio unius est exclusio alterius</A> and <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">ejusdem generis</A>. Connect the statutory language with the canon that could be used to interpret it.</P></QUESTION> <ITEM CATEGORY="1">Use of a firearm in connection with a burglary, robbery, car-jacking or other crime is a felony.</ITEM> <ITEM CATEGORY="2">Use of a firearm in connection with a burglary, robbery, or car-jacking is a felony.</ITEM> <ITEM CATEGORY="1">Federal courts will be closed on the Fourth of July, Veterans Day and other holidays.</ITEM> <ITEM CATEGORY="2">Federal courts will be closed on the Fourth of July and Veterans Day.</ITEM> <ITEMS>Items</ITEMS> <CATEGORY>ejusdem generis</CATEGORY> <CATEGORY>expressio unius est exclusio alterius</CATEGORY> <RIGHT NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 5 of 7"><P>Two of the statutes have only a list of specifics. <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">Expressio unius est exclusio alterius</A> can be used to interpret these statutes. The rule provides that anything not in that list of specifics was intentionally left out and should be interpreted accordingly.</P><P>Two of the statutes have general terms following the list of specifics. <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">Ejusdem generis</A> should be used to determine to what those general terms would apply. The rule provides that the legislature probably intended to limit that general term to the same class as the specifics.</P></RIGHT> <WRONG><P>Two of the statutes have only a list of specifics. <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">Expressio unius est exclusio alterius</A> can be used to interpret these statutes. The rule provides that anything not in that list of specifics was intentionally left out and should be interpreted accordingly.</P><P>Two of the statutes have general terms following the list of specifics. <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">Ejusdem generis</A> should be used to determine to what those general terms would apply. The rule provides that the legislature probably intended to limit that general term to the same class as the specifics.</P><P>Give the question another try.</P></WRONG> <ORDERED>False</ORDERED> <SHUFFLE>True</SHUFFLE> <NOTES><P>04/30/2010 DQ replaced drawlines</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="41" BOUNDS="272,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="If right" DEST="42" BOUNDS="238,159,37"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="If wrong" DEST="41" BOUNDS="285,159,46"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="66" BOUNDS="341,159,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="381,159,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Linguistic 5 of 7" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 6 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Linguistic    5 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Try to solve the following hypothetical question:</P><P>The school rule is that a student taking a final exam can bring in &quot;only pens, pencils, erasers and other test-taking materials.&quot; Jane arrives at the exam with a large bottle of fruit juice which she intends to drink during the exam. Jane claims that she is entitled to take the juice in because it is &quot;test-taking material.&quot; Applying the linguistic canons of statutory interpretation, is Jane correct that her bottle of juice should be allowed into the test because it is a &quot;test-taking material&quot;?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Probably not due to <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">ejusdem generis</A>.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Probably not due to <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">expressio unius est exclusio alterius</A>.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>She probably is right due to <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">ejusdem generis</A>.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>She probably is right due to <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">expressio unius est exclusion alterius.</A></P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK><P>The statutory language, &quot;pens, pencils, erasers and other test-taking materials.&quot; has a general term at the end. So the canon which should be used is the one that applies to such general terms, i.e., <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">ejusdem generis</A>.</P><P>Answers B and D refer to the wrong canon. </P><P>Under ejusdem generis, the general term should be interpreted as applying only to the class of the specifics that preceded it. Here the specifics are pens, pencils and erasers. These are tools actually used to take the test. Juice cannot be used to take the test, so juice does not fit within this classification. So answer C, saying it did, is incorrect.</P><P>So applying ejusdem generis, Jane is probably not entitled to bring in her juice. That means answer A is correct.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 6 of 7"><P>A is the best answer. </P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 6 of 7"><P>A is the best answer.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="3" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 6 of 7"><P>A is the best answer.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="4" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 6 of 7"><P>A is the best answer.</P></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="42" BOUNDS="1416,443,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="A" DEST="43" BOUNDS="1404,491,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="B" DEST="43" BOUNDS="1430,491,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="C" DEST="43" BOUNDS="1456,491,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="D" DEST="43" BOUNDS="1482,491,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="43" BOUNDS="1508,491,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Linguistic 6 of 7" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 7 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Linguistic    6 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>The school rule is that the person taking a final exam can bring in &quot;pens, pencils, erasers, clocks, tissues, ear-plugs, and other test-taking materials.&quot; Bonnie arrives at the exam with a large bottle of fruit juice which she intends to drink during the exam. Bonnie claims that under the rule, she is entitled to take the juice in because it is &quot;test-taking material.&quot; Applying the linguistic canons of statutory interpretation, is Bonnie correct?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Probably yes based on <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">expressio unius est exclusio alterius</A>.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Probably not based on <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">expressio unius est exclusio alterius</A>.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Probably yes based on <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">ejusdem generis.</A></P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Probably not based on <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">ejusdem generis.</A></P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 7 of 7"><P>The list of specifics has been expanded over the list in the prior question's rule. Here the list includes not just materials used in actually taking the test (pens, pencils and erasers), but also exam-support materials (clocks, tissues and ear-plugs), So the class which defines the general term is also expanded to include exam-support materials. Juice to keep up the test-taker's energy level would seem to fit into this classification. So &quot;C&quot; is the best answer.</P><P>Expresio unius est exclusio alterius applies only to a list of specifics that is not followed by a specific term. So it does not apply in this situation.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 7 of 7"><P>The list of specifics has been expanded over the list in the prior question's rule. Here the list includes not just materials used in actually taking the test (pens, pencils and erasers), but also exam-support materials (clocks, tissues and ear-plugs), So the class which defines the general term is also expanded to include exam-support materials. Juice, which would keep up the test-taker's energy level, would seem to fit into this classification. So &quot;C&quot; is the best answer.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="3" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 7 of 7"><P>The list of specifics has been expanded over the list in the prior question's rule. Here the list includes not just materials used in actually taking the test (pens, pencils and erasers), but also exam-support materials (clocks, tissues and ear-plugs), So the class which defines the general term is also expanded to include exam-support materials. Juice to keep up the test-taker's energy level would seem to fit into this classification. So &quot;C&quot; is the best answer.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="4" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 7 of 7"><P>This list of specifics has been expanded over the list in the prior question's rule. Here the list includes not just materials used in actually taking the test (pens, pencils and erasers), but also exam-support materials (clocks, tissues and ear-plugs), So the class that defines the general term is also expanded to include exam-support materials. Juice, which would keep up the test-taker's energy level, would seem to fit into the class of exam-support materials. So &quot;C&quot; is the best answer. </P></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="43" BOUNDS="1416,526,109">  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="A" DEST="50" BOUNDS="1404,574,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="B" DEST="50" BOUNDS="1430,574,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="C" DEST="50" BOUNDS="1456,574,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="D" DEST="50" BOUNDS="1482,574,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="50" BOUNDS="1508,574,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Process 2 of 4" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Process 3 of 4" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Process    2 of    4"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Here is an example to illustrate this concept. </P><P>Congress provides funds for federal programs by passing <B>appropriations acts</B>. Normally, appropriations acts deal only with funding provisions. So one would not expect to find any provisions in an appropriations act except funding provisions. Including any other provision would be unusual.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="44" BOUNDS="1634,194,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="38" BOUNDS="1674,242,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="liberal construction" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 4 of 6" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="liberal construction"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>The term &quot;liberal construction&quot; has nothing to do with the &quot;liberal&quot; and &quot;conservative&quot; of the political spectrum. The term is used in statutory interpretation to identify an approach to interpreting statutes and to distinguish it from &quot;strict construction.&quot; Under liberal construction, words are to be given a broad meaning while under strict construction words are to be given a narrow meaning.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="45" BOUNDS="54,331,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Introduction 7 of 7" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Introduction    7 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>You have completed the introductory section of this lesson. What would you like to do next?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Continue on to the next section which considers why the process of statutory interpretation is challenging.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Go back to the Table of Contents. From there, you can go to another section, repeat the introductory section, or exit the lesson.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Why 1 of 12"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents"></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>scoring is disabled</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="46" BOUNDS="544,609,109">  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="A" DEST="3" BOUNDS="558,657,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="B" DEST="67" BOUNDS="584,657,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="610,657,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 12 of 12" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Why   12 of   12"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>You have now completed the section that addresses why the process of statutory interpretation is challenging. What would you like to do next?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Continue on to the next section which examines legislative intent.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Go to the table of contents. From there, you can exit this lesson, repeat this section or go on to another section.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Legislative Intent 1 of 5"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents"></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>scoring is disabled</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="47" BOUNDS="762,1024,109">  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="A" DEST="20" BOUNDS="776,1072,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="B" DEST="67" BOUNDS="802,1072,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="828,1072,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Legislative Intent 5 of 5" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Legislative Intent    5 of    5"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>You have now completed the section on legislative intent. What would you like to do now?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Continue on to the next section which addresses the plain meaning rule and the purpose approach to statutory interpretation.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Return to the Table of Contents. From there you can exit the lesson, repeat the section on legislative intent, or go on to any other section in this lesson.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 1 of 7"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents"></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>scoring is disabled</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="48" BOUNDS="980,443,109">  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="A" DEST="9" BOUNDS="994,491,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="B" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1020,491,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1046,491,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Plain Meaning 7 of 7" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Plain Meaning    7 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>You have completed the section on the plain meaning and the purpose approach. What would you like to do now?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Go on to the next section which addresses linguistic canons of interpretation.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Return to the Table of Contents. From there you can exit the lesson, repeat this lesson, or go on to any other section of this lesson.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 1 of 7"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents"></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>scoring is disabled</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="49" BOUNDS="1198,609,109">  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="A" DEST="10" BOUNDS="1212,657,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="B" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1238,657,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1264,657,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Linguistic 7 of 7" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Linguistic    7 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>You have completed the section on linguistic canons of interpretation. Remember that the two linguistic canons illustrated here are not the only ones. These two are the best known and most often used today, but there are a number of others. We are not getting into them because this is an introductory lesson.</P><P>What would you like to do now?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Continue on to the next lesson which addresses how the legislative process may affect statutory interpretation.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Return to the Table of Contents. From there you can exit this lesson, return to the section on linguistic canons, or go on to any other section.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Process 1 of 4"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents"></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>scoring is disabled</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="50" BOUNDS="1416,609,109">  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="A" DEST="11" BOUNDS="1430,657,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="B" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1456,657,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1482,657,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Process 4 of 4" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Process    4 of    4"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>You have completed the section that reveals how legislative process can be used in statutory interpretation. What would you like to do next?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Go on to the next section. It deals with substantive canons of interpretation, i.e., canons that are based on the subject matter of the statute.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Go back to the Table of Contents. From there you can exit the lesson, repeat this section, or go to any of the other sections.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Substantive 1 of 3"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents"></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>scoring is disabled</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="51" BOUNDS="1634,360,109">  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="A" DEST="12" BOUNDS="1648,408,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="B" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1674,408,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1700,408,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Substantive 3 of 3" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Substantive    3 of    3"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>You have completed the section on substantative canons of interpretation. Congratulations. You are almost to the end of the lesson. So what would you like to do now?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Continue on to the next section which deals with statutes that affect the interpretation of other statutes.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Return to the Table of Contents. From there you can exit the lesson, return to the lesson on substantive canons, or go to any other section.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 1 of 6"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents"></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>scoring is disabled</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="52" BOUNDS="1852,277,109">  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="A" DEST="17" BOUNDS="1866,325,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="B" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1892,325,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="1918,325,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Statutes 6 of 6" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Statutes    6 of    6"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>You have finished this section. What would you like to do next? </P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>That is the last substantive section of this lesson. The next section is a review question. Let's give that a try.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Return to the Table of Contents. From there, you can exit the lesson, return to the section on statutes that you've just finished, or go to any other section.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Review 1"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents"></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>scoring is disabled</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="53" BOUNDS="2070,526,109">  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="A" DEST="59" BOUNDS="2084,574,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="B" DEST="67" BOUNDS="2110,574,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="2136,574,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Introduction 2 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Introduction 3 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Introduction    2 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Before we begin, let's clear up some confusion that may be produced by the term, &quot;statutory construction.&quot; It does not have anything to do with building a statute. Nor is it the process of writing or drafting the statute or enacting it into law. </P><P>&quot;To construe&quot; something means to give that thing meaning. So &quot;construing a statute&quot; is the process of giving that statute meaning,<I> i.e</I>., interpreting it. The act of construing is &quot;construction.&quot; Since the word &quot;construction&quot; also means the act of building, we have a term with two different meanings. </P><P>You should expect to see and hear the terms &quot;to construe a statute,&quot; &quot;construing a statute,&quot; and &quot;statutory construction &quot; and you now know what is meant. In this lesson, we will use &quot;interpretation&quot; rather than &quot;construction&quot; to avoid any confusion.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="54" BOUNDS="544,194,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="13" BOUNDS="584,242,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Why 3 of 12" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Check Boxes" NEXTPAGE="Why 4 of 12" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Why    3 of   12"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Consider a term used frequently in the legal profession, &quot;cite.&quot; Put a check mark in the box next to its correct meaning. </P></QUESTION> <BUTTON>Category</BUTTON> <DETAIL><P>To call upon a person to appear in court.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>To identify the location of information or a quotation.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>The ability to see, i.e., one of the five senses.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>The location of the source of information or a quotation.</P></DETAIL> <CHECKS>1-1,2-1,4-1</CHECKS> <RIGHT NEXTPAGE="Why 4 of 12"><P>&quot;Cite&quot; has a number of meanings including all of those listed except the sense of &quot;sight&quot; which sounds like it but is spelled differently.</P></RIGHT> <WRONG><P>There is more than one correct answer. To get this marked correct, you have to check all the correct possibilities. Don't leave any out, but don't include an incorrect one. With that hint, give the question another try.</P></WRONG> <NOTES><P>image - Copyright CALI 2005. Drawing by Eric Molinsky. </P><P>06/14/2010 Jess added ADA tag</P></NOTES> <PICTURE SRC="ButIThoughtYou.jpg">drawing of two old men looking at each other with confused expressions</PICTURE> <MAPPER ID="55" BOUNDS="762,277,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="If right" DEST="28" BOUNDS="750,325,37"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="If wrong" DEST="55" BOUNDS="797,325,46"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="28" BOUNDS="853,325,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Plain Meaning 4 of 7" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose Buttons" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 5 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Plain Meaning    4 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>To illustrate these comments, reconsider the hypothetical question.</P><P>In response to a citizen petition complaining about children being attacked by animals in public parks, the state legislature passed a statute prohibiting animals from being brought into public parks. No child has ever been attacked by a guide dog. In fact, studies show that: (1) disabled children in parks are safer if they are accompanied by guide dogs and (2) no guide dog has ever bothered a child in a park. </P><P>Bill is a blind person. He walked into a park assisted by his guide dog. </P><P>We have already determined that a court using the plain meaning approach will determine that Bill violated the statute. Suppose, instead, that the court uses the purpose approach. Would the court still find that BIll has violated the statute?</P></QUESTION> <BUTTON>Yes</BUTTON> <BUTTON>No</BUTTON> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 5 of 7"><P>I disagree. The purpose of the statute was to protect children in public parks. The purpose is not furthered by keeping guide dogs out of parks. They apparently do not pose a threat. In fact, disabled blind children will be safer in the park if they are accompanied by their guide dogs. So the purpose of protecting children will, in fact, be furthered by allowing guide dogs to be brought into the park.</P><P>Therefore, a court applying the purpose approach should conclude that the legislature did not intend to prohibit blind people from bring guide dogs into the park and the statute should be interpreted to be consistent with that intent.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="2" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 5 of 7"><P>I agree. The purpose of the statute was to protect children in public parks. The purpose is not furthered by keeping guide dogs out of parks because they apparently do not pose a threat. </P><P>Moreover, blind people, including blind children, will be safer in the park if they are accompanied by their guide dogs. So the purpose of protecting children will, in fact, be furthered by allowing guide dogs to be brought into the park.</P><P>So a court applying the purpose approach could conclude that the legislature did not intend to prohibit blind people from bring guide dogs into the park and the statute should be interpreted to be consistent with that intent.</P></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>10/09/2009 DQ changed path to match rest of lesson, where response goes right to next page. </P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="56" BOUNDS="1198,360,109">  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="Yes" DEST="62" BOUNDS="1204,408,26"/>  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="No" DEST="62" BOUNDS="1240,408,22"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="62" BOUNDS="1272,408,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Ejusdem generis" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 3 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Ejusdem generis"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P><B>Ejusdem generis</B> means of the same class. It is used to narrow a general term that is at the conclusion of a list to the same category as the specific terms in the list. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="57" BOUNDS="54,386,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Expressio unius" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 4 of 7 (4/30/2010 replaced drawlines)" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Expressio unius"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P><B>Expressio unius est exclusio alterius</B> means that the inclusion of one excludes others. It is also known as the rule of <I>negative implication</I> or the rule of <I>backspin</I>. Under this canon, when a statute provides specifics, particularly a list of specifics, any specific not mentioned is not included by implication. </P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="58" BOUNDS="54,441,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Review 1" TYPE="Text Entry" STYLE="Text Essay" NEXTPAGE="Review 2" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Review    1"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Let's try a little review question to pull these concepts together. A state legislature was concerned that there might be a rise in the number of teenagers smoking marijuana. So the legislature enacted a statute that provided:</P><P>&quot;The driver's license of any person smoking marijuana shall be suspended and may not be reinstated until that person has completed court-ordered anti-drug training.&quot;</P><P>Bob was arrested for allegedly smoking marijuana. Charges were dropped when Bob agreed to testify against the person who sold him the marijuana. However, Bob received a notice from the Department of Motor Vehicles that his driver's license has been suspended. Because Bob was never charged, no anti-drug training was ordered or could be ordered for him by any court. Bob argues the statute should not be interpreted to require his license be suspended.</P><P>What are the arguments for, and against, Bob's position?</P></QUESTION> <CORRECTTEXT><P>The prosecutor would invoke the plain meaning rule. The legislature provided that the license of a person smoking marijuana would be suspended. Bob smoked marijuana. Therefore, his license should be suspended.</P><P>Bob would argue that the golden rule exception applies because the plain meaning rule will produce an unreasonable result of unnecessary hardship and it would be ridiculous to mandate suspension for a person who wasn't charged when a person who was convicted could escape suspension by taking the court-ordered anti-drug training. The exception allows for the use of the purpose approach to interpret the statute. In the alternative, Bob should urge the court to use the soft plain meaning rule under which the plain meaning is just a factor to be considered in addition to the legislative purpose of preventing teenage drug use which would be better accomplished by encouraging him (and others) to avoid the license suspension by turning in state's evidence and testifying against the drug sellers. Suspending his license under these circumstances will discourage others from testifying.</P><P>Bob could also invoke the rule of lenity. License suspension is a punishment, so the statute providing for it should be construed in favor of the one who would be punished. The result is that the statute should be interpreted to apply only if convicted of any marijuana-related offense for which court-ordered anti-drug training could be ordered.</P></CORRECTTEXT> <FEEDBACK><P>You have completed all the sections of this lesson. You can complete the lesson by reading the Conclusion.</P></FEEDBACK> <MAPPER ID="59" BOUNDS="2288,111,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="64" BOUNDS="2328,159,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="NCCUSL" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Statutes 5 of 6" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="NCCUSL"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>The National Conference of Commissioners on Uniform State Laws is an independent body whose purpose is to promote the uniformity of the laws among the states. The purpose is to be accomplished by drafting legislation to be presented to the various state legislatures and encouraging the enactment of those proposals. The success of proposals has varied. Some version of the Uniform Commercial Code has been adopted by every state. However no state ever adopted the Uniform Land Transactions Act or its successor the Uniform Land Security Interest Act. Most Uniform Acts have an adoption rate somewhere between these extremes.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="60" BOUNDS="54,496,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Legislature" TYPE="Pop-up page" STYLE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Introduction 5 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Legislature"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>The federal legislature (the United States Congress) and most state legislatures are bicameral. That means they are divided into two houses. To be enacted into law, the identical bill must get a positive vote in both houses. Nebraska is unique in that it has a unicameral legislature, i.e., its legislature has only one house. Enactment in Nebraska requires a positive vote only in that one house. Unicameral legislatures are the general rule in local governments such as cities and counties. Their enactments are called ordinances.</P></TEXT> <MAPPER ID="61" BOUNDS="54,551,109"> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Plain Meaning 5 of 7" TYPE="Book Page" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 6 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Plain Meaning    5 of    7"><TEXT ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Can a court decide to ignore the plain meaning and use the purpose approach instead? Traditionally, the answer was &quot;no.&quot; If a statute had a plain meaning, a court had to use it unless doing so would produce injustice, unnecessary hardship, or a ridiculous result. This was known as the &quot;golden rule exception.&quot; Courts following this traditional approach cannot ignore the plain meaning in favor of the purpose approach until they have first made a finding that the exception applies. </P><P>Some courts, however, have opted for the &quot;soft plain meaning&quot; approach. Under this approach, the court considers the plain meaning to be just one factor to be weighed in the process of determining legislative intent. The legislative purpose behind the statute is simply another factor to be considered. No finding that an exception applies need be made before considering the legislative purpose or any of the other tools or methods of statutory interpretation.</P><P>These are two different approaches. They turn on how much weight is to be given to the plain meaning. That's a philosophical decision. You may find one approach or the other mandated by a decision of the state's supreme court or you may find a jurisdiction's cases include a mixture of the two, depending on who was on the appellate panel and who wrote the opinion.</P></TEXT> <NOTES><P>05/31/2006 DQ fixed typo</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="62" BOUNDS="1198,443,109">  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="63" BOUNDS="1238,491,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Plain Meaning 6 of 7" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 7 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Plain Meaning    6 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Attorney is planning her oral argument before the state supreme court. The issue concerns the proper interpretation of a recent state statute. Attorney is confident of winning. In the report of the Senate committee that reviewed the bill, there are clear statements about the bill's purpose by the bill's sponsors that support her position and nothing in the legislative history supports the position of her opponent. However, she is concerned about how to use the committee report in her argument because the court below ruled in favor of her opponent based on the statute's plain meaning.</P><P>Her research reveals that one justice of the supreme court is a textualist and that the majority of the others follow the traditional approach to the plain meaning rule.</P><P>Should she start her argument by pointing out what's in the legislative history and hammer away at that throughout her argument?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>No. </P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Yes</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK><P>The majority of the judges follow the traditional approach to the plain meaning rule. So they will only consider the purpose found in the legislative history if (1) there is no plain meaning because the statute is ambiguous or (2) the golden rule exception applies. So before focusing on what she found in the legislative history, Attorney should first make sure that the justices understand why the statute is ambiguous or why the plain meaning will produce injustice, unnecessary hardship, or a ridiculous result. If the justices feel bound by the plain meaning, then convincing them of the purpose won't win the case.</P><P>The textual justice is another story. The textualist justice will not be interested in hearing what is in the legislative history because textualists reject the use of legislative history in the statutory interpretation process. If that justice's vote is necessary, Attorney had better find another line of reasoning</P><P>However, if a majority of the justices on this court used the soft plain meaning approach, then starting with the evidence of purpose found in the legislative history might be a good idea. After all, the purpose and the plain meaning are just factors to be considered in determining the legislative intent.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="RIGHT" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 7 of 7"><P>Correct.</P></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="WRONG" NEXTPAGE="Plain Meaning 7 of 7"><P>Incorrect.</P></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>10/09/2009 DQ changed path to match rest of lesson, where response goes right to next page. </P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="63" BOUNDS="1198,526,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="A" DEST="49" BOUNDS="1212,574,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="B" DEST="49" BOUNDS="1238,574,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="49" BOUNDS="1264,574,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Review 2" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Choose List" NEXTPAGE="Contents" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SORTNAME="Review    2"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Now that you've finished the review question, what would you like to do?</P></QUESTION> <DETAIL><P>Complete the lesson by going to the Conclusion.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Go back to the Table of Contents.</P></DETAIL> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="1" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Conclusion"></FEEDBACK> <FEEDBACK BUTTON="1" DETAIL="2" GRADE="INFO" NEXTPAGE="Contents"></FEEDBACK> <NOTES><P>scoring is disabled</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="64" BOUNDS="2288,194,109">  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="A" DEST="2" BOUNDS="2302,242,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="13" NAME="B" DEST="67" BOUNDS="2328,242,16"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="67" BOUNDS="2354,242,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Introduction 6 of 7" TYPE="Prioritize" STYLE="PDrag" NEXTPAGE="Introduction 7 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Introduction    6 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Here are the basic facts of this hypothetical question. </P><P>Bob operates a restaurant in the city of Atlantis which is located in Western County, Florida. In one of the rooms of the restaurant, he operates a bar. He is wondering if he can allow his customers to smoke in that bar even though there is a law prohibiting smoking in the restaurant. </P><P>Match the facts with the appropriate statement. </P></QUESTION> <ITEM CATEGORY="1">Florida enacted a law that prohibits smoking in restaurants.</ITEM> <ITEM CATEGORY="2">Western County, Florida enacted a law that prohibits smoking in restaurants</ITEM> <ITEM CATEGORY="2">The City of Atlantis enacted a rule prohibiting smoking in restaurants.</ITEM> <ITEM CATEGORY="3">Bob leased space in a mall for his restaurant.  In the lease is a clause that prohibits smoking in restaurants.</ITEM> <ITEMS>Items</ITEMS> <CATEGORY>This is a state statute.  How to go about interpreting it is the subject of this lesson.</CATEGORY> <CATEGORY>This is a local ordinance.  For interpretation purposes, it is generally treated like a statute despite the differences in the enactment process. So its interpretation is covered by this lesson.</CATEGORY> <CATEGORY>This is not a statute, so how to interpret it is not covered by this lesson.</CATEGORY> <RIGHT NEXTPAGE="Introduction 7 of 7"><P>Good work. You've completed this section.</P></RIGHT> <WRONG NEXTPAGE="Introduction 7 of 7"><P>You have missed something. A clause in a lease is not law, so it could not be a statute or an ordinance. The law passed by the state would be classified as a statute. The law passed by a county or city would classified as an ordinance. </P><P>The approach to interpreting an ordinance is generally the same as the approach to interpreting a statute. That's what will be covered by this lesson. However, interpreting leases is a different matter entirely and not discussed by this lesson.</P></WRONG> <ORDERED>False</ORDERED> <SHUFFLE>False</SHUFFLE> <NOTES><P>04/30/2010 DQ added to replace drawlines; modified interface specific language</P><P>06/22/2016 DQ changed path of wrong choice from &quot;Introduction 5 of 7&quot; to &quot;Introduction 7 of 7&quot; </P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="65" BOUNDS="544,526,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="If right" DEST="46" BOUNDS="532,574,37"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="If wrong" DEST="46" BOUNDS="579,574,46"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="46" BOUNDS="635,574,30"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
<PAGE ID="Linguistic 4 of 7" TYPE="Multiple Choice" STYLE="Radio Buttons" NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 5 of 7" NEXTPAGEDISABLED="False" SCORING="Totals" SORTNAME="Linguistic    4 of    7"><QUESTION ALIGN="AUTO"><P>Below are samples of statutory language. The headings are two canons of interpretation, <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">expressio unius est exclusio alterius</A> and <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">ejusdem generis</A>. Match the statutory language with the canon that could be used to interpret it.</P></QUESTION> <BUTTON>ejusdem generis</BUTTON> <BUTTON>expressio unius est exclusio alterius</BUTTON> <DETAIL><P>Use of a firearm in connection with a burglary, robbery, car-jacking or other crime is a felony.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Use of a firearm in connection with a burglary, robbery, or car-jacking is a felony.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Federal courts will be closed on the Fourth of July, Veterans Day and other holidays.</P></DETAIL> <DETAIL><P>Federal courts will be closed on the Fourth of July and Veterans Day.</P></DETAIL> <CHECKS>1-1,2-2,3-1,4-2</CHECKS> <RIGHT NEXTPAGE="Linguistic 5 of 7"><P>Two of the statutes have only a list of specifics. <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">Expressio unius est exclusio alterius</A> can be used to interpret these statutes. The rule provides that anything not in that list of specifics was intentionally left out and should be interpreted accordingly.</P><P>Two of the statutes have general terms following the list of specifics. <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">Ejusdem generis</A> should be used to determine to what those general terms would apply. The rule provides that the legislature probably intended to limit that general term to the same class as the specifics.</P></RIGHT> <WRONG><P>Two of the statutes have only a list of specifics. <A HREF="popup://Expressio unius">Expressio unius est exclusio alterius</A> can be used to interpret these statutes. The rule provides that anything not in that list of specifics was intentionally left out and should be interpreted accordingly.</P><P>Two of the statutes have general terms following the list of specifics. <A HREF="popup://Ejusdem generis">Ejusdem generis</A> should be used to determine to what those general terms would apply. The rule provides that the legislature probably intended to limit that general term to the same class as the specifics.</P><P>Give the question another try.</P></WRONG> <NOTES><P>04/30/2010 DQ added to replace drawlines; modified interface specific language</P></NOTES> <MAPPER ID="66" BOUNDS="1416,360,109">  <BRANCH KIND="14" NAME="If right" DEST="42" BOUNDS="1382,408,37"/>  <BRANCH KIND="15" NAME="If wrong" DEST="66" BOUNDS="1429,408,46"/>  <BRANCH KIND="11" NAME="Next" DEST="42" BOUNDS="1485,408,30"/>  <BRANCH KIND="18" NAME="Links" DEST="" BOUNDS="1525,408,33"/> </MAPPER></PAGE> 
</BOOK>

